Guide to the North Carolina Self-Portrait Photography Collection, 1930-1996 RL.00938
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Self-Portrait Photography collection
1930-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
RL.00938
8 Linear Feet
The North Carolina Self-Portrait Photography Collection includes copy negatives, contact sheets, prints, information sheets, agreements, and voice recordings created as part of the North Carolina Self-Portrait Project, undertaken to build an archive of images and other materials documenting the experiences of African American families in the South. The photographs were assembled by requesting copy photographs from African American families primarily in North Carolina, but a few locations in Mississippi were also included. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Approximately 2000 Items
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The North Carolina Self-Portrait Photography Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999, 2001, and 2007.
Biographical Note
The Center for Documentary Studies, an interdisciplinary educational organization affiliated with Duke University, is dedicated to advancing documentary work that combines experience and creativity with education and community life. Founded in 1989, CDS connects the arts and humanities to fieldwork, drawing upon photography, filmmaking, oral history, folklore and writing as catalysts for education and change.
The North Carolina Self-Portrait project (NCSP) was directed by Alex Harris at the Center For Documentary Studies, Duke University. The NCSP project was modeled after a similar project conducted by the Center for the Study of Southern Culture at the University of Mississippi. The objective of these projects was to photograph the family pictures of African Americans, and to record on audio tape the family member's descriptions of the photographs.
Collection Overview
The North Carolina Self-Portrait Collection, 1993-2000, contains paper documents, audio cassettes, contact sheets, slides, negatives, and photographs, all relating to the work of the NCSP project. To build the collection of images of African Americans in the South, project staff visited African American families primarilyy in North Carolina locales, but also in Mississippi, and requested copies of original family photographs created from 1900 to 1990, giving back quality reproductions to the families for their own collections.
The collection is particularly rich in materials related to the private and professional lives of African Americans living in the South during the first half of the 20th century. The images contain subjects typical to family photograph albums, including: candid and formal portraits, weddings, anniversaries, award ceremonies, school pictures, athletic teams, vacations, leisure activities, and other aspects of domestic life. In addition, many of the families whose photographs were copied were active members of religious and social organizations. Some of the distinct and more heavily represented organizations are the Arabian Shriners, New Bern Isiserettes, Eastern Stars, Young Men's Institute in Asheville, the A.M.E. Church, as well as employees of the NC Mutual Insurance Co. The North Carolina portion of this project was primarily conducted in the geographic locations of New Bern, James City, Durham, Asheville, and Southern Pines.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access note
Portions of the collection are restricted: the Black Highlander materials are open for research access but cannot be reproduced.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series: Papers, Photographic Prints, Contact Sheets, Negatives and Slides, Exhibition Prints, and Audio Cassettes.
Slides (photographs); Negatives (photographs); Black-and-white photographs; Contact sheets; North Carolina -- Social conditions; Audiocassettes; African American families -- Mississippi -- Portraits; Mississippi -- Social conditions; Photography -- United States -- History; African American families -- North Carolina -- Portraits; African Americans -- Mississippi -- Portraits; Portrait photography -- United States; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Portraits; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Papers Series, 1993-1996
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of files and records stemming from the project to create the North Carolina and Mississippi Self-Portrait Collection. Includes information sheets for each subject or family; notes from the photography sessions; grant proposals and budgets; correspondence; photocopies of loaned photos; and other project records. Also includes computer disc with information sheets.
  - North Carolina Individual Families Subseries
    This subseries contains paper format materials created when photographing the family albums of North Carolina residents. The material is arranged alphabetically, by the collection's creator, using a three letter code for the last name of the participant family, with some exceptions. Each folder contains an information sheet that provides an itemized description of the photographs that were copied, and may contain notes used when printing the photographs contained in other series in this collection.
    - Master Disk for North Carolina Information Sheets (Box 1)
    - Information Sheets for North Carolina Color Materials (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Helen Adams, ADA 0194-1, ADA 0194-2 (Box 1)
    - Agnes and Tommie Brown, AgnesBro-1, AGN-2 BRO (Box 1)
    - Isadore and Julene Allen, ALL-1093 (Box 1)
    - Black Highlander Collection, BHC- 1193 (Box 1)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      (RESTRICTED: images may not be reproduced.)
    - Kaye Brown and Annie Chadwick, BRO-1, BRO-2 (Box 1)
    - Mr. Robert and Artelia Bryant, BRY-1, BRY-2, BRY-3 (Box 1)
    - Jessie Carr, CAR-1 (Box 1)
    - The Clements, CLE 0294-1, CLE 0294-2 (Box 1)
    - Doris Daniels, DAN 1193-1, DAN 1193-2 (Box 1)
    - Stella Dowdy, DOW 1093 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Ida Franks, FRA 0194-1, FRA 0194-2 (Box 1)
    - Jacquline Shelton Green, GRE-1, GRE-2 (Box 1)
    - Lottie Hainsworth, HAI 1093, HAI 1093-2 (Box 1)
    - Mrs. Mary Hallman, HAL 1093, HAL 1093-2 (Box 1)
    - Ms. Bessie Hasty, HAST 1093 (Box 1)
    - Phyllis Jones Sherill, JON 1193-1, JON 1193-2, JON 1193-3, JON 1193-4 (Box 1)
    - Erline McQueen, MCQ 1193-1, MCQ 1193-2, MCQ 1193-3 (Box 1)
    - Omega Ray Wilson, OME-1 (Box 1)
    - Jesse Ray, RAY 1193-1, RAY 1193-2 (Box 1)
    - Mary Sligh, SLI 1193, SLI 1193-2, SLI 1193-3 (4x5) (Box 1)
    - Ray Trent, TRE-1 (Box 1)
    - Margaret Turner, TUR-1, TUR-2, TUR-3 (Box 1)
  - Office Files Subseries
    Files house records concerning the administration of the NCSP project.
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Publicity (Box 1)
    - Budgets, Grant Proposals, Reports (Box 1)
    - Photocopies of Borrowed Prints (Box 1)
    - Photocopies of Contact Sheets Made in Mississippi (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Photographic Prints Series, circa 1980-1996
  Photographs printed from negatives made by photographing family albums.
  - North Carolina Individual Families Subseries
    This subseries contains photographs made from the albums of families living in North Carolina, and is organized by the same three letter code as the North Carolina Individual Families Subseries located in the Paper Format Series.
    - ADA (Box 2)
    - Agnes Bro (Box 2)
    - ALL (Box 2)
    - BHC (Box 2)
      (RESTRICTED)
    - BRO, Kaye (Box 2)
    - BRY (Box 2)
    - CAR (Box 2)
    - CLE, Clemment (Box 2)
    - DAN (Box 2)
    - DOW (Box 2)
    - FRA-3 (Box 2)
    - FRA-4 (Box 2)
    - GRE (Box 2)
    - HAST (Box 3)
    - JON-1 (Box 3)
    - JON-2 (Box 3)
    - JON-3 (Box 3)
    - JON-4 (Box 3)
    - MCQ (Box 3)
    - OME, Ray Wilson (Box 3)
    - Sligh (Box 3)
    - TRE (Box 3)
    - TUR-1 (Box 3)
    - TUR-2 (Box 3)
    - TUR-3 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs Subseries
    Photographs that at the time of processing could not be directly attributed to a specific family; or photographs in a different format than the photographs in the North Carolina Individual Families Subseries.
    - Loose dry-mounted prints (Box 3)
    - Loose resin-coated prints (Box 3)
    - Loose fiber-based prints (Box 3)
- Contact Sheets Series, 1993-1994
  Contains contact sheets for the projects conducted in North Carolina and Mississippi.
  - North Carolina Individual Families Subseries
    This subseries contains color and black-and-white contact sheets printed from negatives made from the albums of families living in North Carolina, and is organized by the same three letter code as the North Carolina Individual Families Subseries in the Paper Format Series. The color contact sheets are foldered together because they contain images for more than one family. Color images were not made for all of the participant families, if color material exists for a particular family it is noted in the following container list. The Color Contact Master Sheet (located in the Paper Format Series and the color contact sheet folder) is an index of the color contact sheets that can be used locate a corresponding black-and-white image, and to identify the participant family that provided the original image. Because the color contact sheets contain images for more than one family a portion of the contact sheet may be open for research while another portion is closed. The Color Contact Master Sheet can be used to identify the portions of the contact sheets that are closed.
    - Mrs. Helen Adams, ADA 0194-1, ADA 2, color and black-and- white (Box 4)
    - Agnes and Tommie Brown, AGNES BRO-1, AGN-2 BRO, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Isadore and Julene Allen, ALL 1093, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Black Highlander Collection, BHC-1193, black-and-white (Box 4)
      (RESTRICTED: open for access but not to be reproduced)
    - Kaye Brown and Annie Chadwick, BRO-1, BRO-2, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Mr. Robert and Artelia Bryant, BRY-1, BRY-2, BRY-3, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Jessie V. Carr, CAR-1, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - The Clements, CLE 0294-1, CLE 0294-2, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Doris Daniels, DAN 1193-1, DAN 1193-2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Stella Dowdy, DOW 1093, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Mrs. Ida Franks, FRA 0194-1, FRA 0194-2, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Jaquline Shelton Green, GRE-1, GRE-2, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Lottie Hainsworth, HAI 1093-1, HAI 1093-2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Mrs. Mary Hallman, HAL 1093, HAL 1093-2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Ms. Bessie Hasty, HAST 1093, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Phyllis Jones Sherill, JON 1193-1, JON 1193-2, JON 1193-3, JON 1193-4, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Erline McQueen, MCQ 1193-1, MCQ 1193-2, MCQ 1193-3, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Omega Ray Wilson, OME 1, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Jessie Ray, RAY 1193-1, RAY 1193-2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Mary Sligh, SLI 1193, SLI 1193-2, SLI 1193 4x5's 1-20, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Ray Trent, TRE-1, color and black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Mrs. Margaret Turner, TUR-1, TUR-2, TUR-3, black-and-white (Box 4)
  - Mississippi Contact Sheets Subseries
    This subseries contains contact sheets made for the project conducted at the University of Mississippi. Contact sheets made from the albums of participant families living in Mississippi, as well as, images of the participant families themselves are included in this subseries. The negatives used to make the contact sheets contained in this subseries are not included in this collection.
    - 35mm Contact Sheets Folder 1, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - 35mm Contact Sheets Folder 2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - 4x5 Contact Sheets Folder 1, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - 4x5 Contact Sheets Folder 2, black-and-white (Box 4)
    - Photographs of participants, black-and-white (Box 4)
- Negatives and Slides Series, 1993-1994
  This series contains black-and-white negatives and color negatives made from the albums of families living in North Carolina, and is organized by the same three letter code as the North Carolina Individual Families Subseries in the Paper Format Series. This series also contains slides of exhibition quality photographs that were made from both the Mississippi and North Carolina projects.
  - Slides made from exhibition prints (Box 5)
  - Color negatives made in North Carolina, rolls 1-7 (Box 5)
    (Closed portions have been removed.)
  - ADA (Box 5)
  - Agnes Bro (Box 5)
  - ALL (Box 5)
  - BHC (Box 5)
  - BRO (Box 5)
  - BRY (Box 5)
  - CAR (Box 5)
  - CLE (Box 5)
  - DAN (Box 5)
  - DOW (Box 5)
  - FRA (Box 5)
  - GRE (Box 5)
  - HAI (Box 5)
  - HAL (Box 5)
  - HAST (Box 5)
  - JON (Box 5)
  - MCQ (Box 5)
  - OME (Box 5)
  - RAY (Box 5)
  - SLI (Box 5)
  - TUR (Box 5)
  - TRE (Box 5)
- Exhibition Prints Series, circa 1995 and 2000 Oct 15-Dec 3.
  This series consists of matted and unmatted black and white photographs printed from negatives originating in Mississippi and North Carolina; the matted prints were used in exhibitions in 1995 and 2000 at the Center for Documentary Studies, Duke University. Most titles supplied by archivist.
  - Boy scouts standing saluting a flag in a field, 8.5 x 11 7/8 print; 11x14 mat (Box 10)
    Photographer unknown. From the collection of Mrs. Eva Ford, Vicksburg, Mississippi.
  - Faded and torn picture of woman in hat, 8 5/8 x 10 print; 11x14 mat (Box 10)
    Photographer unknown. From the collection of Mrs. Eva Ford, Vicksburg, Mississippi. Copied by Robert Jones. Supported by a grant from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
  - Girl in angel costume, 7 5/8 x 11 1/4 print; 11x14 mat (Box 10)
    Photographer unknown. From the collection of Mrs. Baggs, Jackson, Mississippi. Copied by Robert Jones. Supported by a grant from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
  - Cyrus Nero (right) and classmates at their high school graduation, 1937, Greenwood, Mississippi, 6 3/8 x 9.5 print; 11x14 mat (Box 10)
    Photographer unknown. From the collection of Melvin and Gwendolyn Loper, Jackson, Mississippi. Copied by Robert Jones. Supported by a grant from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
  - Young couple posing for photo, 6 3/8 x 10 5/8 print; 11x14 mat (Box 10)
    Photographer unknown. From the collection of Mr. Roosevelt Cathey, Coldwater, Mississippi. Copied by Robert Jones. Supported by a grant from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
  - Christmas, boy in cowboy outfit with toy guns in front of TV, 7 7/8 x 12.5 print; 16x20 mat (Box 11)
  - Man standing next to short column with book, 7 5/8 x 12 print; 16x20 mat (Box 11)
    From Mrs. Eva Ford, Vicksburg, Mississippi.
  - Exhibition prints, 2000
    Captions supplied by archivist. Some prints are umatted but the majority are in mats. All are black and white prints.
    - Man and child reflected in car window, 14x11 print, unmatted (Box 12)
    - Man with snowball in field of snow, 8x8 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Two children in a playpen outside, 6.75x9.5 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Man wearing military uniform sitting on a chair, 6.75x10.25 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Family portrait in front of a house, 6x10.25 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Train at the lumber yard, 7.75x11.5 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Young girl standing beside a tire, 6x10.5 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Mother kissing a child, 6x8.5 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Man and boy in suits standing beside a car, 7.5x10.75 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Men standing in a circle around a kneeling man, 7.5x10.75 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Young boy and girl wearing Native American headdresses playing outside, 6x9 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Boy sitting on Santa's lap with a gun, 7x11 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Woman standing on a walkway outdoors, 7x10.25 print; 11x14 mat (Box 12)
    - Girl wearing mud hat, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - People at town gathering, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Man working on bicycle, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Elderly man with bow and quiver, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Man in communal shower, alone, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - English lessons in a one-room schoolhouse, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - People sleeping on a night bus, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Man carrying chair in field, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Elderly woman holding a reference book, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Campsite with fire in a coffee can, 16x12 print (Box 13)
    - Laughing woman in curlers, 13x9 print, 20x16 mat (Box 13)
    - People in water for baptism, 12.5x9 print, 20x16 mat (Box 13)
- Audio Cassettes Series, 1993-1994
  This series contains audio cassette recordings of reminiscence and descriptions of the photographs copied from the albums of North Carolina participant families.
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use, and require production of listening or viewing copies. Where digital preservation and access files have been created, they will be listed, and the corresponding digital set may be requested. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Helen Adams (Box 7)
  - Isadore Allen (Box 7)
  - Agnes Brown (Box 7)
  - Kaye Brown (Box 7)
  - Bryant, 2 tapes (Box 7)
  - Jessie Carr/Wilson (Box 7)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Bill Clement (Box 7)
  - Doris Daniels (Box 7)
  - Stella Dowdy (Box 7)
  - Mrs. Ida Franks (Box 7)
  - Jaki Shelton Green (Box 7)
  - Lottie Hainsworth (Box 7)
  - Mrs. Mary Hallman (Box 7, Digital-materials RL00938-SET-0001, Audio-file RL00938-CS-0001.wav)
  - Erline McQueen (Box 8)
  - Jeese Ray (Box 8)
  - Phyllis Jones Sherrill (Box 8)
  - Sligh (Box 8)
  - Mrs. Margaret Turner (Box 8)
  - Omega Ray Wilson (Box 8)